<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breef discour[s] wherin is declared, of y[e] trauailes an[d] miseries of this painful life, &amp; that death is t[he] dissoluer of mans miserie. Gathered out of d[i]uers good writers, by Leonard Staueley. Wh[er]vnto is annexed the authors muse of this life, in English vearse and his prayse likewise of vertue, felicitie and true sentillitie</title>
            <author>[Staveley, Leonard].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23239.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846656</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12947)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1642:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breef discour[s] wherin is declared, of y[e] trauailes an[d] miseries of this painful life, &amp; that death is t[he] dissoluer of mans miserie. Gathered out of d[i]uers good writers, by Leonard Staueley. Wh[er]vnto is annexed the authors muse of this life, in English vearse and his prayse likewise of vertue, felicitie and true sentillitie</title>
                  <author>[Staveley, Leonard].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the long shop adioyning vnto Saint Mildreds Church in the Pultrie by Iohn Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1575?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Only known copy cropped at fore-edge.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A BREEF DISCOVR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> wherin is declared of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trauailes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>miſeries of this painful life, &amp; that death is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> diſſoluer of mans miſerie. Gathered out of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers <hi>good writers, by Leonard Staueley. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto</hi> is annexed the Authors muſe of this life / in Engliſh Vearſe and his prayſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of Vertue / Felicitie and true Gentillitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero. 1. Tuſcul.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <hi>Moriendum eſt omnibus: eſt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> finis Miſeriae in morte.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Death draweth on</l>
               <l>We muſt be gon,</l>
               <l>From Bed to Béer:</l>
               <l>In time repent,</l>
               <l>Thy life ill ſpent,</l>
               <l>Whiles thou art héer.</l>
               <l>For after death</l>
               <l>Hath ſtopt our Breth,</l>
               <l>We ſhall be ſure:</l>
               <l>In Heauen to dwel</l>
               <l>Or els in Hell</l>
               <l>Where paines indure.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London at the long shop adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> vnto Saint Mildreds Church in the Pultrie by <hi>Iohn Allde.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Worshipfull Anci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent</hi> and graue Knight, Sir <hi>Robert VVingfeeld of Letheringham Leonard <hi>Staueley wiſheth encreaſe of worship,</hi>
               </hi> Vertue and Godly ſluing, with <hi>Neſtors</hi> yeeres, <hi>Craeſus</hi> welth, and <hi>Galliens</hi> happy helth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much (Right vvorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) as I finde in ſundry hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries of antiquitie, of the tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes of diuers kindes of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes (vvhich vvant reaſon and vnderſtanding) shovved vnto their Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefactors, and for that I vvere very lothe to be included in the number of vnthankfull Creatures: I haue therfore preſumed by this little trifle, vpon the curteous inclination of your gentle nature vvhich to all men is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, to shovve my ſelf to be an other poore Sinatas vvhoſe good vvil and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes in hart and minde, I truſt you vvil vvay aſvvel in a drop of ſvveet running vvater as if it vvere a gift of ſome precious or more greater value. For as I remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber Eraſmus in his vvittie Appothegmes
<pb facs="tcp:11640:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaith that, Donum quodcunque dat aliquis, proba: &amp; Munerum animus eſt optimus.</p>
            <p>But paraduenture your vvorship vvil mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail vvhy I (bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g one of ſmall or no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) haue attempted to put my Pen to the paper to vvrite of a more vvaightyer matter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my vvittes or learning are able to attaine vnto. The trueth is though I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vvent further then a little in the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Schole (yet by common experience, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bookes, and mine ovvne induſtry and trauel) I haue conceiued ſome thing. For vvhen I conſider the ſundry miſchaunces of fickle Fortune (if any ſuch thing there be:) the miſerable eſtate of mankinde, novv puffed vp in Pompe of all Pleaſures, novv throvvne dovvn into the dungion of all do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lors, anon commeth a flovving flud, by and by a lovve eb vvater: ſo that the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of this vaine fleeting life may be vvell compared to a violent flood, vvhich is quick in ryſing, ſvvift and troubleſome to paſſouer, induring but for a vvhile in one condition and certentie. VVherfore theſe (as the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:11640:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> frutes of my good vvil vvhat ſoeuer they be) I haue dedicated to your vvoorships Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, vnder vvhoſe Sheeld of defence a num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of afflicted members haue ſure ſauegard, and gentle refuge, amongſt vvhome I am one, vvho am bound by double dutie &amp; vvil be preſt (if ſeruice by hand or hart may doo any thing) to you and yours for euer.</p>
            <p>But for aſmuch as the hugenes of the head defaſeth a little ſlender body, and a tedious tale may breed ſome offence, &amp; leſt in length<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning myne Epiſtle I should diſgrace that ſmall thing vvhich follovveth, heer in breef I vvil end, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that a little Muſicque to the heauy hart is often found more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and pleaſant then a great deal of vntu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vvoorships moſte humbly to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund during life, Leonard Staueley.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Verſes Written vpon the name</hi> of the Right woorſhipfull Sir <hi>Robert Wingfeeld Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Regarding right, way wel in minde,</l>
               <l>Of life and death the end of all.</l>
               <l>Beware of freends that are vnkinde.</l>
               <l>And ſeek to kill by curteous call.</l>
               <l>Recoyle from him which layes a net:</l>
               <l>Thy ſilly Soule in ſinne to get.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVith harty looue like wel that frend</l>
               <l>Yn vvhome great vviſdome dooth remain</l>
               <l>Neclecting vice, ſo in the end</l>
               <l>Great gifts of God thou ſure shalt gaine.</l>
               <l>Flee ſwift vvith (Wing) and vvin the (Feeld)</l>
               <l>Extolling Gods vvoord ſtill on bye</l>
               <l>Liue vvel, liue euer, to Vertue yeeld,</l>
               <l>Dred God and Prince, moſte carefully.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Keepe Conſcience pure, and pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to God</l>
               <l>Not liuing like an Epicure,</l>
               <l>If that thou dooſt his heauy rod,</l>
               <l>Great plagues and vvoes thou shalt endure</l>
               <l>Heauens bleſſe the race being gody run</l>
               <l>The guerdon is vvhen life is doon.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Stand ſtedfaſt, L. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the curteous and freendly <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I haue ſeen by diuers and learned woorks (moſte gentle Reader) that there was neuer yet any matter ſo handled / but ſome fault hath eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, ſo for want of ſkill (in mine owne dooings, Lacking the benefit of exact knowledge) I haue ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne a Rouing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any order in my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges. But ſuch as it is I preſent to thy frendly reading, wherin I haue declared ſome parte of mans intolle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable paſſions &amp; frailtie, for redres wherof I ſay that <hi>death is the diſoluer of his miſerable miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I gain thy good woord I haue my deſire, but if I reap thy reproch: thou ſheweſt but thy noyſom nature wherfore (hoping the beſt) I wiſh thee vſe this til time afford better, &amp; as I heer of thy freendly report: ſo wil I write of other matters to thy contentation, profit and pleaſure. <hi>et ſic Vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Savwel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Book to the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Rashly pend, doo ſpring from barren braine,</l>
               <l>A ſimple me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, in proſe for to declare:</l>
               <l>vvhat ſorovves ſovver, vvhat greefs &amp; pi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ching pain</l>
               <l>This life dooth bring, vvherby vve may prepare,</l>
               <l>VVith death to Chriſte avvay fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence to fare,</l>
               <l>VVherfore in gree accept vvhat heer is ſaid:</l>
               <l>Since meer goodvvil vvas cauſe that he it made</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I shovve in breef hovv Vertue vvinneth Fame</l>
               <l>Hovv she alone brings true Felicitie:</l>
               <l>Hovv all that is on earth is nought but vain,</l>
               <l>And hovv vve ought eſteem Gentillitie.</l>
               <l>Miſconſter nothing that thou ſpieſt in me,</l>
               <l>So by that meanes thou vvin'ſt his hart and all:</l>
               <l>In prompteſt vviſe to pleaſure thee at call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Blame not his ſkil,</l>
               <l>for of good vvil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>From him I came:</l>
               <l>as only mean,</l>
               <l>To purge him clean</l>
               <l>of thankles name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As dooth behooue,</l>
               <l>let him thy looue,</l>
               <l>And good vvoord gain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>abandon Spite,</l>
               <l>So maieſt thou quite</l>
               <l>his little pain.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Looue is a ſolace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Ba. He. to the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SWéet is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmel, which pleaſeth all mens ſent,</l>
               <l>Wel can he wryte, which féedeth euery vain</l>
               <l>If this ſmel ſwéet to thoſe who hath it ſent,</l>
               <l>The Author hath his hire for his pain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſhowe and prooue wiſe <hi>Solons</hi> ſaying true,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Til Death, that none can be a happy man:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Good <hi>Staueley</hi> ſhowes by that which dooth enſue,</l>
               <l>And with his pen it prooues, as beſt he can.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If paine for others gaine, deſerue but wel,</l>
               <l>If toyle for common weale be woorthy prayſe:</l>
               <l>Commend the Author then, who ſhowes his ſkil,</l>
               <l>To profit thée, and others, with his phraſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His willing minde to write, doo not repréeue,</l>
               <l>All ſpiteful termes for enuious men reſerue:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Staueley</hi> for his paine, obtain thy looue,</l>
               <l>And wiſh him wel, as wel he dooth deſerue.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>William Brogdon in prayſe of the Authors trauaile.</head>
            <l>MVſe you that liſt from vvhence I came,</l>
            <l>or vvhat good Stauely ment:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>VVhoſe care vvas ſuch to vvoork the vvay,</l>
            <l>for vvhich his time vvas ſpent.</l>
            <l>Read you vvhat he hath careful vvrit,</l>
            <l>and follovv you his lore:</l>
            <l>So death thou shalt learne to contemne,</l>
            <l>that dreaded death before.</l>
            <l>It's follye for to feare that thing,</l>
            <l>vvhich no man can eſchevv:</l>
            <l>Liue then to day as thou vvouldeſt dye.</l>
            <l>ſo Staueley vvilles thee doe.</l>
            <l>He tels thee vvhat thy life it is,</l>
            <l>And vvhat thyne end muſt be:</l>
            <l>To day a man, to morovv none,</l>
            <l>by proofe vve knovve and ſee.</l>
            <l>VVhat troubles are in vvretched life,</l>
            <l>and vvhat hangs ouer head:</l>
            <l>Thou mayſt beholde and heer for ſee,</l>
            <l>vvhich oft thou dooſt not dread.</l>
            <l>VVhich may thee teach for to be vviſe,</l>
            <l>hovv thou heerafter liues:</l>
            <l>Eſchevv the euil, embrace the good,</l>
            <l>as Staueley Counſail giues.</l>
            <l>And ſo farvvel and him doo thank,</l>
            <l>vvhich for thee tooke ſuch paines:</l>
            <l>His ſtudy is not for himſelf,</l>
            <l>but thou the profit gaines.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>If thou this platforme follovv vvil,</l>
            <l>vvhich freendly he beſtovves:</l>
            <l>Then shalt thou ſuerly dye to liue,</l>
            <l>as he in ſequel shovves.</l>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>VV. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Oſwald Speed to the Reder.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS many men, ſo many wittes,</l>
               <l>Some lothe that which other looue:</l>
               <l>And one thing neuer all men fits,</l>
               <l>As this my fréend ſhall prooue.</l>
               <l>Whats ſome mans meat, dooth poyſon ſome:</l>
               <l>And this mans bliſſe is that mans doome.</l>
               <l>In reading ſome condemneth thoſe,</l>
               <l>That in the plaineſt ſort:</l>
               <l>His meaning to them dooth diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>And ſome again report</l>
               <l>Him bleſt, that hath the loftieſt vaine:</l>
               <l>And déem the reſt of barrein braine.</l>
               <l>Another ſort dooth him commend,</l>
               <l>That igmys in midle mean:</l>
               <l>Not much affecting, to offend,</l>
               <l>Nor yet without it clean.</l>
               <l>So one for this, and ſome for that doo call:</l>
               <l>That one man cannot pleaſe them all.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>So he my fréend that writ this Booke,</l>
               <l>Would willingly delight</l>
               <l>All thoſe, that on the ſame doo looke,</l>
               <l>If poſſibly he might.</l>
               <l>He ſéeketh nothing for his pain:</l>
               <l>But Readers liking for to gain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thus fare you vvel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The beſt is ſoone ſaid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſvvell as the vvorſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This all men can tel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It is not beſt made:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That's doon at the firſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>ꝙ Oſwold Speed.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Breef Diſcourſe</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing taſted of the inſatiable ſea of ſowſing ſorowes, and drunk of the careful cup of peruerce pertur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bations aſwel of minde as of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: I finde by proof that dreadfull <hi>Death</hi> (at the naming wherof we tremble, is the diſſoluer of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall cares, troubleſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations &amp; mans moſte miſerable miſery, which to approoue &amp; verifie, let vs firſt call vnto remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berance y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gréeuous gronings of our painful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the time of our natiuitie and education.</p>
            <p>For with what wéeping, wayling, ſobing and ſighing at our firſt enterance into this vale of miſery are we beyond all meaſure moſte grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly afflicted?</p>
            <p>The wery watchings y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colde and long winter nights, the riſing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rocking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lulling, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting &amp; all to aſſwage our paſſions intollerable (which we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarſly knowe although we moſte ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly féel) might be a meane to daunt our haughty harts, &amp; to a bandon our lewd liues, liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in theſe careful calamities oppreſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſorowes innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. But (alas) the firſt Act being finiſhed: we en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter into another kinde of life (ſeuere and ſtrict, as yunglings doo think it) which is going to ſcoole to lern y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precepts of Philoſophie, &amp; wayes to vertu, wherby we become of monſters: men, of ſenceleſſe ſoules: learned lights, (notwithſtanding indéed ſome for the attaining therof bide many a ſharp
<pb facs="tcp:11640:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhower, with carefull and gréeuous correction) which in my minde might often be wun ſooner with mildnes of the Maiſter, then with much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie. When we haue got learning, by reaſon wherof we are called in the Commonwelth, to ſome publike Office, and are the méeter to deale in our priuat affaires, wherin our ſtudyes are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant, our cares continuall, &amp; our ſeruice moſte painful to perfoorme our pretended purpoſes and the diſcharge of our deſired duties. Héer, héer beginneth the tragicall diſcourſe of our grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous gronings &amp; vnfortunat troubles, at which time we think to reap ſome ſolace for our late ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſorowes, but euen then a thouſand of trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles, nay a hel of miſeries vpon our heads, when we think our ſelues in greateſt ſafetie and moſte ſecuritie. For Matrimony ſo preſſeth vs diuers wayes as ſcarſly can we bend our ſtudyes to any good perfection, it taketh away our liked libertie and bringeth theſe incombrances, a Iangling wife, vnquiet Children, brawling (&amp; ſometimes) vntruſtie ſeruants, with innumerable ſuch like torments, therfore all theſe being wel wayed, it may ſéem to the vertuous and honeſt minde, ſuch a warfare of woes, and ſuch a tempeſt of troubles as he might think (and iuſtly ſay) that Death is the looſer of mans moſte lamentable liuing, and the diſſoluer of this wretched ſtate &amp; cares inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable.
<pb facs="tcp:11640:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Morouer there is ſuch Enuy in many, ſuch Pride in generall, and ſuch ſéeking for gain: as the vnquietnes of this life is rather to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, then the pleaſuers therof to be wiſhed or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Doo we not ſée, what priuie detracting, what Enuious maligning, what cruell conſpiring, and all for offices, libertie and lordly liuing. The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman not content with his eſtate, ſéeketh to liue like a Lord rather then an inferior perſon and would become of woorſe then a yeoman: a gentleman and ſo forwards. But marke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes of their mindes, for though no delay may daunt them, no calamities controule them: yet the ſupernall powers perceiuing their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious intention in a moment (by Death) throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe hedlong y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they vainly pretended and deueliſhly attempted.</p>
            <p>O if we which beare the names of men, would but once remember y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of all which is Death, aſſuredly, aſſuredly, then would burning hatred be cold, ſecret matire ly dead and be quite quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſhes. But care to maintaine this life w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> abundance, ambition, pomp, pleaſures, riches, ryot, Libertie, ſame, good fortune, fauour, Fréend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip and goodly countenance is ſo ſuper abundant, as neither can we take our deſired reſt quietly, eat or drink merily, nor doo any moderat action to the contentation of our afflicted mindes, ſo grée<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uouſly
<pb facs="tcp:11640:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> are we turned on the whéel of carking ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re continually. I haue red in the auncient Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls of the renowmed Romains of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuil warres betwixt the puiſant <hi>Pompey</hi> and the coragious <hi>Caeſar,</hi> only for Ambition and deſire of a ſole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, whoſe cares were continuall, the one ſéeking the ouerthrowe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, which Death firſt vſing the Tutors of young <hi>Ptolome</hi> as his inſtrument ſléew <hi>Pompeyus</hi> and ſent his head vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> who ſéeing it: (as writers report) wept. But by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius, Caeſars</hi> life was ſhortly after finiſhed, for they in the ſtately Senat houſe of Roome gaue three and twentie wounds with Penkniues or bodkins moſte cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly bereuing <hi>Caeſar</hi> of his lofty life. O deteſtable deſire of glory, Oh deueliſh deuice for honor, Oh va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſher of Vertue, couldſt thou not be ſatiſfied vntil thou hadeſt the life of goodly <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who (as <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaith) was moſte wiſe in counſail, ful of eloquence, profound in wiſdome, valiant in ſtrength of body, expert in marſhall affaires, and finally in him no exellent qualitie lacked y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was requiſit for any noble man? I could tell you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how <hi>Tiberius</hi> was diſpatched by the hands of <hi>Caligula</hi> for the gouernment and domination of the Empier of the Romains, and how <hi>Caligula</hi> had his deadly wound of <hi>Tiberius Druſus,</hi> who gouerned a ſhort time, the Regiment of that king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:11640:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infinit ſuch like. Thus may you ſée héere that Death hath ended their couetous conceits and ambicious deſires, bridled their wilful wils, and reſtrained their wicked entents. Death is feareful, yea but the loſſe of eternall life is more to be feared, death depriueth vs of honors, world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly renowne, riches, Fréends, Parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: yea but if we forgoe the Crowne of imor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall glory, the heauenly Riches, the company of our déer fréends <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the Prophets, and the ſocietie of our firſt Parents <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; <hi>Eue,</hi> and their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>Seth, Enos, Kenam, Mchalael, Iered Henoch,</hi> and <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> who liued in this Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage nine hundreth thréeſcore &amp; nine yéeres, this is a greater loſſe &amp; much more to be feared. Death aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doneth our delicate delights, our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Paſtimes, our worldly ſolace, &amp; taketh from vs all our bagges golde of &amp; ſiluer, our treaſures, our famous buildings w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the reſt of our ioyes. Yea but in ſtéed of them it reſtoreth vs to a celeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall place fol of bleſſednes &amp; inſpekable felicities which no eye hath ſéen,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor 2.9.</note> no eare hath herd, no hart can conceiue, nor no tung able to vtter. In this place is a heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Ieruzalem where all ioyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comporable are to be found, and ſorowes vtterly exiled. But peraduenture ſome one wil ſay, I liue a quiet life, I haue the good gifts of Fortune, ſhe neuer frowneth on me, my neighbours enuey
<pb facs="tcp:11640:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> not my eſtat of worldly felicitie nor my happy procéedings, and I haue mountaines of welth and no man hateth me but I haue many Fréends by reaſon of my golde, and therfore by this means I can procure my eſtate, pleaſure, helth, life and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to my liking. O vain man, dooſt thou not knowe that thy ſtate is ſo much the more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by how much the more thou eſtéemeſt of thy ſelf and thoſe tranſitory things? For I aſſure thée moſte wretched is he that neuer hath taſted any miſfortune, and he is hated of the Gods that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer féeleth any troubles <hi>Demetrius</hi> calleth a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et life without aduerſitie <hi>Mare mortuum,</hi> a dead Sea. <hi>Pollicrates</hi> a tirant of the Samians, whoſe good Fortune was ſuch as he neuer felt any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce in all his life time ſauing towards his death, who being wery of his continuall ioy and gladnes, towing in a veſſell for his pleaſure into the depth of the Chanell and mening to turne his preſent good hap to changeable &amp; futer ill fortune, wilfully caſt a precious Ring of golde hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pearl in it of ineſtimable value into the waues therof, which a hungry fiſh ſnapped vp the ſame in ſted of other féeding, which béeing preſently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with Fiſhermen &amp; preſented into the Kichin of <hi>Pollicrates</hi> for her ſinguler rarenes: the Cooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pping y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> belly vnawares found this Ring, took it and deliuered it to his maiſter. Although <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrates</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> did now ride on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> top of Fortunes whéel, yet at the laſt the whéel turned and he had a great fall, for in the warres which were betwéen him and <hi>Darius</hi> King of the Pertians, <hi>Orantes</hi> the chéef Captain or Lieutenant of <hi>Darius</hi> tooke him priſoner, &amp; after moſte painful and terrible torments: cauſed him to be honge vpon a gibet vpon the top of a ſtéep hill, or mighty mountaine. O blinde &amp; vnſtable fortune. Had it not béen bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>Pollicrates</hi> now and then to haue taſted ſome of thy ſower ſops of ſorow, and ſometimes to haue droonk of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bitter drink of Aduerſitie then altogither in his braueſt iollitie not only to loſe his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e but alſo his déer life in moſte ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner? As y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> then deltſt with him: ſo ſince thou haſt vſed others thy gueſts in like ſort.</p>
            <p>But yet you think that golde can redéem you from gréet, Siluer from ſorowe, and déeds from Death, no I tell you they are rather means to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten your diſpatch, then to linger your delay. For (as <hi>Bion</hi> reporteth) <hi>Arriſtippus</hi> a very wiſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher had a Seruant who was ouer charged with the waight and charge of his Maiſters mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, therfore bidden by his maiſter to caſt away the ouerplus and carry that which he might with his eaſe, which doon: <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> happening to be on the Sea with Pirats threw all his Golde and Siluer into the waues therof, ſaying: better it
<pb facs="tcp:11640:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> were that all this géere be throwne away by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtippus</hi> then <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> by them: meaning that the kéeping of the money might procure him a diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mall day he béeing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> company of ſuch falce and fained fréends.</p>
            <p>Not much vnlike to this I finde (as the worthy Poets record in their moſte ſacred Verſes,) how <hi>Arion</hi> the exellent and cuning Muſition, who for to encreaſe his knowledge in forren contries, and to augment his eſtate in gathering golde, for ſooke <hi>Leſbos</hi> his owne natiue ſoyle and Contry, and ſayling into <hi>Scicile</hi> remained there a ſeaſon, from thence he traueled into <hi>Italie,</hi> where hauing got his wiſhed deſire of gaine, and pretending to paſſe to <hi>Corinth</hi> being a Ship boord in moſte ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as he thought with his owne contrie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they vnderſtanding what riches he had: ſought by all meanes priuily how to ſlay him: but he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their intent: deſired of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take his golde and other treaſures and ſaue his life, which they would not agrée vnto, but graunted him that he ſhould throwe him ſelf into the waues of the Sea hedlong and ſo ſtoppe his breth for that he ſhould not bewray their miſcheuous Act of Robbery, wherfore with abundance of teares: he requeſted the Marriners, nay rather. Théeues and Pirats (for no other term can I better giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to grant him his lamentable Lute and eke his mourning
<pb facs="tcp:11640:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Roab, which béeing obtained, he ſung to his ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Lute a ſory ſong, and ſo amiddeſt the ſurg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sea did ſée the face of Death yet being aliue. But for all that he was deliuered by the help of a Dolphin fiſh who preſently receiued him on her back and moſte ſafely conuaied him a ſhore when he leaſt looked for any ſuch mater.</p>
            <p>I remember that the renowned Poet <hi>Maro</hi> in his Eneidos of the deſtruction of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous Citie of <hi>Troy</hi> writeth how the ancient and wiſe King <hi>Priamus</hi> fearing leſt the mightie Gréekes ſhould ouerthrowe and vtterly deſtroy all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> regall blood and Iſſue there: ſent his yungeſt ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne <hi>Pollidorus</hi> to his coſen <hi>Pollimneſtor</hi> being a King, hauing a great ſome of Golde with him to miniſter vnto the Infant neceſſaries. <hi>Polimneſtor</hi> made much of <hi>Pollidorus</hi> ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as his Father <hi>Priamus</hi> liued, but he being dead: the cruell Tirant for the grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines of his golde, ſlew him moſte vnnaturally to his ſhame, diſhonor, reproch, and perpetuall in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>famie. Wherin we may perceiue what little ſaue gard is in golden riches, &amp; how vnſtable fortune is, ſomtimes fauning, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times frowni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſomtime content, ſomtimes diſpleaſed, and laſtly the little looue of fained fréends &amp; vnkind kinſmen for their priuate profit how it is ſoon forgotten and ended, ſo that we may wel think, it is better to reſt from our Labours then with paine continually to toyl
<pb facs="tcp:11640:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt nature, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon miſerie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnknowne paines, the pinching penurie, the ſobbings, the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowings the trauelings, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toylings, the ſower Bread of heauynes, the bitter drink of careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the afflictions, as impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, derth, Fire and ſwoord, which before our eyes we rufully doo beholde, the innocent opreſſed, the poore man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, the rich man regarded, Falſhod fauored, Trueth neglected &amp; all goodnes quite deuoured, dooth or may driue vs to think y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> happy and thriſe happy is he that hath paſſed this laborſome Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth in the pathes of Vertue, goodnes &amp; honeſty, and come to the happy Hauen of reſt &amp; quietneſſe which is through Death the diſoluere of mans miſery. For what other thing meanes the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they paint out Vliſſes, tedious troubles, his perilous paſſages, ſomtimes lighting on <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemus</hi> a terrible Giant redy to deuower him, ſomtimes on the wanton Dame <hi>Calipſo</hi> redy to allure him, otherwhiles paſſing by the ſhoares where the ſubtel Sirens were redy to drowne his Barke by the incha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tment of their meruelous Mellody, for the reſiſting wherof (being gouerned by the graue aduice of prudent <hi>Pallas</hi>) he was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine to ſtop his eares with wax, to binde him ſelf to the Maſt of the ſhip &amp; to feed of the ſwéet hearb <hi>Molie</hi> which was giuen him by <hi>Mercury</hi> to auoid all the incantations of <hi>Circe,</hi> with the reſt of like
<pb facs="tcp:11640:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> trechery? Nothing I ſay but to paint out vnto vs (as in a glaſſe) that Man is a mirror of miſery, ſubiect to many hard aduentures, and in daunger of many perrils: Sathan our olde Enemie redy to pray on vs if our owne mighty captain Chriſte were not (in our diſtreſſes) redy to defend vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſubtil aſſaults, without all doubt wée ſhould ſoone become Bondſlaues to all ſinne and iniquitie, the wanton Allurements and wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked entiſements of Dame Pleaſures with her mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſing mates are ſo dreſſed vp in gallant brauery as hardly can we ſaue our Barkes and bodyes from drowning in the waues and woorks of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vanitie, were it not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our great God <hi>Iehouah</hi> the heauenly wiſdome by his good Counſaile dooth giue vs Vertuous Precepts of good liuing to the contrary. I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not forget the notable miſfortunes and euill chaunces of <hi>Oedipus</hi> (written by <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides</hi>) in ſlaying his Father <hi>Laius</hi> marying his owne Mother <hi>Iocaſta</hi> of whom he begat his two infortunat ſonnes <hi>Polynices</hi> and <hi>Eteocles,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the Citizens of <hi>Thebes</hi> had exiled their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: fel in contention one with another for the ſeat of gouernment. For the gréef of theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wickednes <hi>Oedipus</hi> plucked out his owne eyes and became an exile, and would often if his Daughter <hi>Antigone</hi> had not hindered him with gliſtering blade wrought his owne finall deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:11640:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> but he often wiſhed to dye in vaine, yet at the laſt he was with a flame of lightning from heauen ſudenly ſtrooken to death. The mening as we may partely gather by ſence &amp; reaſon is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wickednes of our deſires in <hi>Venus</hi> deueliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes are ſo great y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> attaining therof) we wil not let to murther our Parents, kinſmen &amp; fréends yea &amp; then to mary in our owne blood and conſanguinitie, whervpon it comes to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ofſpring, our children or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of them througth the ſinne of the Parents violently and with all rigor ſéek by all means to percecute one another, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to Death. All which deteſtable dealings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſéen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thundering <hi>Iupiter:</hi> he of his mercy ſtriketh vs vnawares with his Rod of correction and whippeth vs with his ſcourge of Vengeance by lightenings, thunderings, earthquakes, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, ſtrange noyſes, rumors of warres, viſions, inundations of waters, Peſtilences, new and ſtrange diſeaſes called Gentle warnings, and ſomtime ſudden Death to the'nd we might repent vs of our ſinne and be the more redier when aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Atropos ſhall with her deadly darte ſommon vs before the great and terrible Iudge, either to our ſaluation if we repent and amend: or els to our condemnation if we liue and dye without re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentance. Now what is the life of man wherof he ſo much boſteth? I wil anſwer partly with <hi>Arriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totle,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the pray of Time, the play of Fortune, the image of vnconſtancie, the ſlaue of Enuy, the ſea of worldly calamitie: a fading flower, a buble of water, a blaſt of winde, a fléeting ſhadow, a ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ſmoke, a péeuiſh pilgrimage: a ſlumbering ſléep (which as graue <hi>Homer</hi> tearmeth it) is the brother of Death, a Stage play the Acts wherof are vncertain and the length before we come to the Cataſtrop or end of our Comicall action is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſed with infinit miſchefes, the relefer where of is dolful Death that inuincible Champion. For euen as he which ſaileth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sea by wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, time, and tides whether he be ſitting or ſtanding, lying or going, ſléeping or waking at laſt (all perils paſſed:) entreth the wiſhed port of ſaftie. So the life of man by courſe of age and yéeres wil he nil he (how ſoeuer he ſpend his tickled time:) conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually is caried to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of his painful dayes, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> finiſhing of his carefull courſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> happy har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>borow of eternall life, for as life flieth a way with the wings of time: ſo Death draweth on with the féet of age. But foraſmuch (as <hi>Enius</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth) that that Death is not to be lamented the which immortall Fame foloweth. Therfore he which hath ſung much is not the beſt Muſicion, nor he that hath gouerned the Ship longeſt is the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Pilot, nor he that hath béen longeſt at the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie is the beſt ſtudent: but he which hath
<pb facs="tcp:11640:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> doon it the ſooneſt, quicklyeſt, and perfecteſt. So to knit vp in bréef (if alredy I haue not béen to tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) I wil end ſaying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not he which liueth long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is moſte bleſſedeſt becauſe of his ſiluer heres and long time: but he which hath liued wel and ſoonſt trod his footſteps in the path of Vertue, and dyed an honorable Death, is the man that may be accounted moſte hapyeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Death diſſolueth Dollors.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Authors muſe vpon this life in manner of a Dittie.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  </hi> Muſing in my meſtiue minde,</l>
               <l>of this vaine fléeting life:</l>
               <l>By perfect proofe this doo I finde,</l>
               <l>tis nothing els but ſtrife.</l>
               <l>Which when I ſée the pinching, paine</l>
               <l>wherwith poore men are preſt:</l>
               <l>I déeme him happieſt that hath this gaine,</l>
               <l>by Chriſte eternall reſt.</l>
               <l>For héer I ſée our cares abound,</l>
               <l>and ſorowes ſtil encreaſe:</l>
               <l>And neuer lin til vnder ground,</l>
               <l>our corps doo lye at eaſe.</l>
               <l>Our labor then is ended ſure,</l>
               <l>and bleſſedſt is that wight.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>That greateſt gréefs did here endure,</l>
               <l>and led a life moſte right.</l>
               <l>For héer ſuch ſpitefulnes dooth raine,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſwelling Pride aloft:</l>
               <l>Such ſéeking all for worldly gain.</l>
               <l>ſuch ſinne ſo déerly bought.</l>
               <l>Such carking cares to kéep this life,</l>
               <l>in braueſt port and Fame:</l>
               <l>Such ſéeking ſtil for pleaſures ryfe,</l>
               <l>ſuch follyes fond and vaine.</l>
               <l>Such breaking ſléeps, ſuch tugging toyle,</l>
               <l>ſuch watchings and ſuch wiles:</l>
               <l>Such ſéeking one of others foyle,</l>
               <l>ſuch teares of Crocodiles.</l>
               <l>Such laying traps for th'innocent,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſéeking of his blood:</l>
               <l>Such ſubteltie, when trueth is ment,</l>
               <l>ſuch ill, ſuch little good.</l>
               <l>Such woorking woe to harmeles harts,</l>
               <l>ſuch cloking Vice and ſinne:</l>
               <l>Such playing of moſte cruell partes,</l>
               <l>ſuch luſtes our liues are in.</l>
               <l>Such framing of ſwéet hunnyed talk,</l>
               <l>ſuch luring of the wicked wil:</l>
               <l>Such going wrong, that few right walke,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſights the ſoule to ſpil.</l>
               <l>Such ielious fits, ſuch frantick partes,</l>
               <l>ſuch anger all for nought:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Such cloſe deſeits in holow harts,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſecret miſchéefs wrought.</l>
               <l>Such facyng of fine forgid tales,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſwearing all for pence:</l>
               <l>Such falſhood bothe in waights and ſcales,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſauing of expence.</l>
               <l>Such little hoſpitallitie vſed,</l>
               <l>ſuch pinching of the poore:</l>
               <l>Such forſing them to be abuſed,</l>
               <l>ſuch Vice doon euery ower.</l>
               <l>Such haunting of vile Venus trulles,</l>
               <l>ſuch brawling for their cauſe:</l>
               <l>Such cutting, ſlaſhing, knocking ſkulls,</l>
               <l>ſuch breaking of the lawes.</l>
               <l>Such Auarice in euery man,</l>
               <l>ſuch Vſury out of meaſure:</l>
               <l>Such toſſing of <hi>Liaeus</hi> Can,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſpending of their treaſure.</l>
               <l>Such biting with malicious tunges,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſcoffing at the wiſe:</l>
               <l>Such ſlothfulnes, ſuch open wronges,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſtormes doo ſtill ariſe.</l>
               <l>As when I think vpon this life,</l>
               <l>which nothing is (I ſay:)</l>
               <l>But only cares and mortall ſtrife,</l>
               <l>and ſmoke that flyes away.</l>
               <l>Then happy ten times bleſt is he,</l>
               <l>whoſe ruthful race is run:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And dooth enioy Felicitie,</l>
               <l>when all his cares are doone.</l>
               <l>Which mightie <hi>Ioue</hi> graunt vs I pray</l>
               <l>The true Felicitie:</l>
               <l>That we may at our ending day,</l>
               <l>Receiue his great glory.</l>
               <l>And that likwiſe héer in this vale,</l>
               <l>of ſorowes and of mone:</l>
               <l>We may enioy without ten faile,</l>
               <l>heauens bliſſe when life is gon.</l>
               <l>Our gratious Quéen Elizabeth,</l>
               <l>doo kéep O Lord we pray:</l>
               <l>In glorious pomp, and after Death,</l>
               <l>in ioyes that reſt ſhe may.</l>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <trailer>Life is ſtrife.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>His prayse of Vertue, Felicitie, <hi>and Ientillytie.</hi> To the curteous and gentle Reder.</head>
               <l>THeſe ſimple lines which heer I written haue</l>
               <l>Declare the force of Vertues good effect:</l>
               <l>(Good Reader) beare with rudenes mine I craue,</l>
               <l>For here therby no man I wil detect.</l>
               <l>Vprightly iudge and then I need not feare:</l>
               <l>But thou with it in freendly ſort wilt beare.</l>
               <l>Iudge iuſtly,</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>In prayſe of Vertue.</hi> Vertue only bringeth Felicitie.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough <hi>Apollos</hi> filed phraſe,</l>
               <l>and <hi>Pallas</hi> learned ſkill:</l>
               <l>Within my breſt took neuer place,</l>
               <l>to féed my muſe at wil.</l>
               <l>Yet I like <hi>Pan</hi> in rurall rithme,</l>
               <l>for good wil that I beare:</l>
               <l>Vnto the race of Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>wil wright as ſhall appéer.</l>
               <l>It is not Fame ne flattering force,</l>
               <l>ne hoordes of heaped golde:</l>
               <l>But onely Vertue forceth me,</l>
               <l>this ſentence to vnfolde.</l>
               <l>Dame Vertue ſhe that heauenly Quéen,</l>
               <l>and Perragon of price:</l>
               <l>Is only cauſe that ſilly ſoules,</l>
               <l>to honor doo ariſe.</l>
               <l>She bringeth true felicitie,</l>
               <l>and Vice ſhe dooth expell:</l>
               <l>She teacheth how to feare the Lord,</l>
               <l>and ſaue thy ſoule from hell.</l>
               <l>I read a wiſe Philoſopher,</l>
               <l>which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hight:</l>
               <l>In ſtately ſtile, hath left her force,</l>
               <l>apparant to our ſight.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Saying: that Vertue apteſt is,</l>
               <l>to thoſe of youthfull race:</l>
               <l>A pleaſant thing to ancient men,</l>
               <l>to Riche a goodly grace.</l>
               <l>And to the poore ſhe profit bringes,</l>
               <l>aduauncing him ful hye:</l>
               <l>For Vertue only is the cauſe,</l>
               <l>of true Felicitie.</l>
               <l>Vnnoble men ſhe noble makes,</l>
               <l>and glory is their hap:</l>
               <l>Whoſe chaunce is ſuch to take their eaſe,</l>
               <l>in Vertues lulling lap.</l>
               <l>A ſolace ſhe to woful wights,</l>
               <l>whome carking cares oppreſſe:</l>
               <l>She bringes them perfect Pacience,</l>
               <l>and makes their gréef ſéem leſſe.</l>
               <l>Who ſowes the ſéeds of Vertue ſwéet,</l>
               <l>ſhall reap eternall Fame:</l>
               <l>And true Fame ouercommeth Death,</l>
               <l>through Vertue this we gaine.</l>
               <l>A Sage of Gréece was aſked once,</l>
               <l>what thing to man was beſt:</l>
               <l>Euen Vertue (anſwered he) becauſe,</l>
               <l>in her conſiſts great reſt.</l>
               <l>Without the which no good thing may</l>
               <l>once wrought or ſpoken be:</l>
               <l>For ſhe alone brings perfect bliſſe,</l>
               <l>and true Felicitie.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Solon</hi> tolde rich <hi>Craeſus</hi> King,</l>
               <l>it was not flowing welth:</l>
               <l>Ne ſtrength of men, ne <hi>Tagus</hi> ſands,</l>
               <l>Ne <hi>Gallens</hi> mery helth.</l>
               <l>Ne Lordſhips great, ne honors hye,</l>
               <l>ne Pleaſures hunnyed bait:</l>
               <l>That happy made his ſtiffing dayes,</l>
               <l>his frail and brittle ſtate.</l>
               <l>But if he made a godly end,</l>
               <l>and vertuouſly did dye:</l>
               <l>He, he, it is that knowes the vſe,</l>
               <l>Of true Felicitie.</l>
               <l>But now who vertue dooth frequent?</l>
               <l>who ſéeks this virgin pure?</l>
               <l>Euen men of baſeſt Parents born,</l>
               <l>whom Honors doo allure.</l>
               <l>Minerua ioyn'd with Diligence,</l>
               <l>makes many woorthy be:</l>
               <l>Becauſe that Vertue giues the light,</l>
               <l>of true Felicitie.</l>
               <l>The ancient race of Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>haue wun theire Shéelds of Armes:</l>
               <l>Through Vertue and through valiancie,</l>
               <l>defending Prince from harmes.</l>
               <l>But now a dayes ſome Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>doo giue bothe ſpeare and ſhéeld:</l>
               <l>Although indéed they neuer came,</l>
               <l>in any foughten féeld.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Nor yet by Counſail graue at home,</l>
               <l>did profit Common welth:</l>
               <l>But ſought their owne vtillitie</l>
               <l>and eke their priuate helth.</l>
               <l>Golde makes the Heraldes paint ſuch foorth,</l>
               <l>as liketh beſt their haps:</l>
               <l>Yet Apes are Apes though golden Roabs,</l>
               <l>oft times be on their backs.</l>
               <l>True Gentlemen of worthy race,</l>
               <l>through Armor, Speare and Shéeld.</l>
               <l>Haue woon their Armes by dint of ſwoord,</l>
               <l>and puſh of Pikes in féeld.</l>
               <l>But now (alas) I muſt lament,</l>
               <l>that Gentlemen of Fame:</l>
               <l>Let paſſe their ancient Gentery,</l>
               <l>forgetting clean the ſame.</l>
               <l>Some ſcrape vp goods by crafty meanes,</l>
               <l>Some royatly all ſpend:</l>
               <l>Some through exceſſe of pounſing pride,</l>
               <l>are brought to balefull end.</l>
               <l>By thouſand meanes good Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>are brought to dire decay:</l>
               <l>The reaſon is, that vertues loare,</l>
               <l>in them dooth beare ſmall ſway.</l>
               <l>Vpſtarts contrarily, attend,</l>
               <l>on Vertues rayall traine:</l>
               <l>From ſtep to ſtep, from grace to grace,</l>
               <l>til honors ſtep they gaine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Tis better farre a mean man born,</l>
               <l>in Vertue to exſéed:</l>
               <l>Then one who Vice dooth ſtill frequent,</l>
               <l>though Gentle man indéed.</l>
               <l>For nobleneſſe begins in him,</l>
               <l>and in the other dye:</l>
               <l>Which dooth appéer that Vertue brings</l>
               <l>the true Felicitie.</l>
               <l>Who now is the true Gentleman?</l>
               <l>euen bée (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid)</l>
               <l>Whome Nature with <hi>Mineruas</hi> ſkill,</l>
               <l>to Vertues lore hath made.</l>
               <l>If any man to praiſe thou chaunce,</l>
               <l>becauſe he Gentle is:</l>
               <l>His Parents and his Anceſtors,</l>
               <l>thou prayſeſt them iwis.</l>
               <l>It is not Parents progenie,</l>
               <l>(As <hi>Ouid</hi> dooth vs tell:)</l>
               <l>But Vertue maketh Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>alone for to excell.</l>
               <l>Wherfore to Gentle men I write,</l>
               <l>your ancient bloods renew:</l>
               <l>With Vertuous Artes and Gentleneſſe,</l>
               <l>bid filthy Vice adieu.</l>
               <l>And as the names of Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>deſeruedly you haue:</l>
               <l>So frame your liues that you may paſſe,</l>
               <l>with Vertue hence to graue,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Let Iuſtice mixt with Mercyes méed,</l>
               <l>And Wiſdome be your guide:</l>
               <l>Riches contemn, and Pleaſures hate,</l>
               <l>from Faith doo neuer ſlide.</l>
               <l>Pride, Couetouſneſſe, Ambition,</l>
               <l>Vnreuerentneſſe likewiſe:</l>
               <l>Vaine glory, Diſcord, Enuy eke,</l>
               <l>at any hand deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Be humble to inferiors,</l>
               <l>and haue a lowly hart:</l>
               <l>Then wil the common people ſay,</l>
               <l>a Gentle man thou art.</l>
               <l>Séek learnings déep Philoſophie,</l>
               <l>and peace doo thou enſue:</l>
               <l>Hate ireful rage and tirannie,</l>
               <l>and Backus bliſſe eſchew.</l>
               <l>So in the end this glorious Gem,</l>
               <l>Dame Vertue will thée giue:</l>
               <l>A Garland of Immortall Fame,</l>
               <l>wherby thou aye mayſt liue.</l>
               <l>For after Death our Vertues raines,</l>
               <l>wherby we neuer dye:</l>
               <l>But finde that ſhe alone it is,</l>
               <l>bringes true Felicitie.</l>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Vertue winneth Woorship.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A pretty pamphlet of faithful <hi>Freendſhip.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He truethleſſe truſt of fained fréends,</l>
               <l>the wayward wily wayes:</l>
               <l>The déep deceits of hollow harts,</l>
               <l>which hap in theſe our dayes.</l>
               <l>The ſilly ſoule ſo ſoone betraid,</l>
               <l>the Poore man ſo oppreſt:</l>
               <l>That ſcarce Rich <hi>Diues</hi> wil him giue,</l>
               <l>a Crum to be refreſht.</l>
               <l>Theſe things doo mooue my meſtiue Muſe,</l>
               <l>of Fréendſhip to declare:</l>
               <l>That it a Vertue is wherwith,</l>
               <l>no Iewell may compare.</l>
               <l>The Spring wherby our life is fed,</l>
               <l>the Iewell of our ioye:</l>
               <l>The very meane which helps the hart,</l>
               <l>all ſorowes to deſtroy.</l>
               <l>In time of great proſperitie,</l>
               <l>a pleaſure to the minde:</l>
               <l>A ſolace in Aduerſitie,</l>
               <l>a faithful Fréend we finde.</l>
               <l>Fine <hi>Tullie</hi> termd a faithful fréend</l>
               <l>to be another I:</l>
               <l>As who ſhould ſay like to my ſelf,</l>
               <l>in euery propertie.</l>
               <l>A faithfull fréend is ſuch a one,</l>
               <l>as makes thy ſore his ſmart:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>The pricking of thy finger eke,</l>
               <l>the pearſing of his hart.</l>
               <l>Thy miſery his meſtiue moue,</l>
               <l>thy paine his preſent gréef:</l>
               <l>Thy ſorowe ſower his hatefull hap,</l>
               <l>thy helth his ſole releef.</l>
               <l>In doutful dangers thou ſhalt finde,</l>
               <l>that he wil doo thée good:</l>
               <l>And for thy ſake not ſtint at all,</l>
               <l>to ſpend bothe life and blood.</l>
               <l>He ſticketh faſt at all aſſayes,</l>
               <l>miſchaunces him approoue:</l>
               <l>To be of truſtie <hi>Troylus</hi> kinde,</l>
               <l>in fréendſhip and in looue.</l>
               <l>Its he who abſent ſeemes to be,</l>
               <l>in preſens euery houre:</l>
               <l>Yea dead, aliue and all this ſprings,</l>
               <l>through this moſte fragrant flower.</l>
               <l>The very mean wherof dooth mooue,</l>
               <l>the fearſe Barbarians minde:</l>
               <l>In myſerye abooue all welth,</l>
               <l>a faithful fréend we finde.</l>
               <l>It is not flaſhing flames of fire,</l>
               <l>his freendſhip may reſtrain:</l>
               <l>Ne <hi>Midas</hi> muck, no <hi>Irus</hi> gréef,</l>
               <l>ne bliſſe ne pinching pain.</l>
               <l>But like the pureſt Franckenſence,</l>
               <l>which yéeldeth foorth a ſmell:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore ſwéeter in the flame then out</l>
               <l>experience this dooth tel.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r as the golden Glaſſe woorme ſhines,</l>
               <l>moſte brighteſt in the night:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e miſerye tryes faithful fréend,</l>
               <l>to be a truſty wight.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r not vnlike the redolent Roſe,</l>
               <l>of dulſed Dammaſk kinde:</l>
               <l>Which ſwéeter is in ſtil then ſtalke,</l>
               <l>as we by proofe doo finde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thagoras</hi> did once pronounce,</l>
               <l>that Fréendſhip looue doth binde</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in two bodyes faſt conioyne,</l>
               <l>an equallneſſe of minde.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Poet <hi>Empedocles</hi> ſaid,</l>
               <l>that all things firme did ſtand:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea all the world and all therin,</l>
               <l>vpholde by Fréendſhips hand,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gratitude neclecting looue,</l>
               <l>and Fréendſhip put to flight:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his followes then an end of all,</l>
               <l>life is diſſolued quite.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertue begets this Iuell rare,</l>
               <l>and it conſerues alwayes:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> very fréendſhip Vertue is,</l>
               <l>(as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayes.)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a League as neither time,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y péecemele may deuide:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Nor Fancies fond affects nor fraud,</l>
               <l>infrindge at any tide.</l>
               <l>A Fréend wil hazard life and lims,</l>
               <l>yea goods yea welth and all:</l>
               <l>Ere that hée ſee his fréend take harme,</l>
               <l>in daunger dyre to fall.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Damons</hi> looue to <hi>Pithias,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>example is leſe to vs:</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Niſus</hi> and <hi>Euriolus</hi> looue,</l>
               <l>the Poet dooth diſcuſſe.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Gyſippus</hi> his fréend did prooue.</l>
               <l>a truſty <hi>Titus</hi> true:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Theſeus</hi> to <hi>Pirotheus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>like fréendſhip did enſue.</l>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Sipio</hi> and <hi>Lelius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>in fréendſhip did excell:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Palemon</hi> with <hi>Crates</hi> eke,</l>
               <l>for fréendſhip bare the bell.</l>
               <l>The looue of fréendly <hi>Lincius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(<hi>Ioſephus</hi> writeth plaine:)</l>
               <l>Vnto his déere <hi>Artorius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>to their eternall fame.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ionathas</hi> ſau'd <hi>Dauids</hi> life,</l>
               <l>in ſacred writ we finde:</l>
               <l>So that no Iewell here on earth,</l>
               <l>is like a fréendly minde.</l>
               <l>It is not ſtrength of mightie men,</l>
               <l>that fréendſhip dooth obtaine:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e heaps of Golde, but faithfulneſſe,</l>
               <l>and kindenes it dooth gain.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>indenes annext with Gentle déeds,</l>
               <l>true fréendſhip dooth enflame:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Loyall looues fidelitie,</l>
               <l>dooth ſtill increaſe the ſame.</l>
               <l>The likelyneſſe of manners makes,</l>
               <l>coniunction of the minde:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Vertue ioynd with honeſtie,</l>
               <l>true fréendſhip firme dooth binde.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ike wil to like (the Prouerb ſaith,)</l>
               <l>the Turtle looues her make:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd mournes til death for want of féehr,</l>
               <l>and all for fréendſhips ſake.</l>
               <l>But hot looue ſoone is could (ſome ſay,)</l>
               <l>the ſequell is too true:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd faire woords makes fooles faine,</l>
               <l>which alwayes dooth enſue.</l>
               <l>The pureſt wine makes Vinagre,</l>
               <l>to be of ſharpeſt kinde:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd déepeſt looue to deadlieſt hate,</l>
               <l>is often chaungd we finde.</l>
               <l>True triall prooueth truſtineſſe,</l>
               <l>in truſt is treaſon found:</l>
               <l>Who climbs vpon a rotten bough,</l>
               <l>may catch a fatall wound.</l>
               <l>For in aduerſitie we ſée,</l>
               <l>the flattering faithleſſe féend:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>To ſtart a ſide and here vs make,</l>
               <l>in miſery our end.</l>
               <l>As Swallowes comes in ſomer time,</l>
               <l>when pleaſures growe full gréen:</l>
               <l>But when the winters rage comes on,</l>
               <l>are no where to be ſéen.</l>
               <l>So fained fréends when welth a bounds</l>
               <l>wil ſpeak what we doo ſay:</l>
               <l>But when as Fortune frownes on vs,</l>
               <l>they quite doo flée away.</l>
               <l>Then are they like the Bée which hath,</l>
               <l>the hunnie ſwéet by kinde:</l>
               <l>Within her mouth, but yet ſhe beares,</l>
               <l>a ſmarting ſting be hinde.</l>
               <l>For as they erſt with ſugred woords,</l>
               <l>did promiſe golden grapes:</l>
               <l>So now their Tippets clene they turne,</l>
               <l>and leaue vs in the brakes.</l>
               <l>In fellowſhip lyes falſhood hid,</l>
               <l>and fraud in fréendly lookes:</l>
               <l>And vnder ſwéet and hunnied baites,</l>
               <l>doo lurke the harmful hookes.</l>
               <l>An painted pots ſwéet poyſon is,</l>
               <l>wherby our bane dooth riſe:</l>
               <l>In cléereſt ſtreme the vglieſt Tode,</l>
               <l>in graſſe the Serpent lyes.</l>
               <l>The filthy rotten bones ſome time,</l>
               <l>in curious graue we finde:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in a <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſe there lyes,</l>
               <l>a priuie galling minde.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Siren</hi> with her ſiluer ſongs,</l>
               <l>whoſe notes doo oft allure:</l>
               <l>The ſilly ſhip man to the ſands,</l>
               <l>his death for to procure.</l>
               <l>Or as the Crocodile who yeelds,</l>
               <l>a ſory ſolemn ſound:</l>
               <l>Til ſhe haue brought the wailing wight,</l>
               <l>lye ſprawling on the ground.</l>
               <l>The Spider weaues a curious web,</l>
               <l>the ſilly Flye to wile:</l>
               <l>The woolfe dooth weare a ſmiling face,</l>
               <l>the Lambe for to beguile.</l>
               <l>The Panthers breth dooth ſwéeteſt ſmell,</l>
               <l>when pray ſhe dooth enſue:</l>
               <l>I fréendly face meanes falſeſt faith,</l>
               <l>experience is to true.</l>
               <l>In fréendſhip all that ſéemes to ſhine,</l>
               <l>it is not pureſt Golde:</l>
               <l>Nor euery woord is Goſpell ſure,</l>
               <l>which Friers haue vs tould.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leaden Dagger oft is found,</l>
               <l>with in a golden ſheath:</l>
               <l>And ſure a flattering faithleſſe fréend,</l>
               <l>dooth bring vs preſent death.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n extrem néed when Fortune faites,</l>
               <l>few fréends a man ſhall finde:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>But then like to the Réed they ſhake,</l>
               <l>with euery blaſt of winde.</l>
               <l>In Priſon if thou chaunce to lye,</l>
               <l>when worldly welth dooth faile:</l>
               <l>My Skin is néerer then my Shirt,</l>
               <l>this ſuer wil be their tale.</l>
               <l>Wherfore if I may Counſaile giue,</l>
               <l>I wiſh thée to take héed:</l>
               <l>Of him who beares a knife to kill,</l>
               <l>yet weares a fréednly wéed.</l>
               <l>Let no faire woords dim perfet ſight,</l>
               <l>but carefully beware:</l>
               <l>Full ſwéetly dooth the Fouler ſing,</l>
               <l>to catch the Bird in ſnare.</l>
               <l>Be ſure whom as thou mindſt to make,</l>
               <l>to be thy faithful fréend:</l>
               <l>Thou eat a peck of ſalt with him,</l>
               <l>and thus I make an end.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>No fraud to fained freendship. <hi>ꝙ. Leonard Staueley.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:11640:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ The cenſure of a freend concerning <hi>the former Verſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ith freendships lore you doo commend,</l>
                  <l>accoumpting it a Ievvell rare:</l>
                  <l>And that ſo highly you extend,</l>
                  <l>ſuch prayſe as nothing may compare.</l>
                  <l>Vnto the ſame (ſo much of price:)</l>
                  <l>and truſt me, I like your deuice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Indeed firm freendship novv a dayes,</l>
                  <l>is very geaſon I ſpeke plaine:</l>
                  <l>For Sicophants deuiſe ſtill vvayes,</l>
                  <l>falcely to flatter, fleere and faine.</l>
                  <l>For deep diſſembling novv dooth reſt:</l>
                  <l>doutleſſe almoſte in euery breſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But vvhat mean I to ſpeake ſo blunt,</l>
                  <l>as to condemn in generall?</l>
                  <l>Although ſome faithleſſe freends be vvunt,</l>
                  <l>to haue diſembling at their call.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſome doo hap on ſuch a freend:</l>
                  <l>as faithfull bides vntil the end.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Prayſe after proofe. Quoth Iames Yates.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:11640:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
